Finding Aid for Leroy and Lael Cappaert papers 1947-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Leroy and Lael Cappaert papers 1947-2002
Cappaert, LeRoy.
6 linear feet
LeRoy Cappaert was a teacher and Democratic city councilman from Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1964-1970, delegate to the 1968 Democratic National Convention, and member of the Coalition for Peace in Central America, and organization established to provide assistance to Ann Arbor's sister city, Juigalpa, Nicaragua. Lael Cappaert was a librarian, also active in political and community causes. Papers and notebooks concerning LeRoy's election campaigns for the city council, his council activities, his work as delegate at the Democratic National Conventions of 1964 and 1968, and the 1968 Presidential campaign of Senator Eugene McCarthy, his work with the Coalition for Peace in Central America; memoirs of his wife Lael Cappaert, pictorial history of their daughter Andrea Lael Cappaert; audio-visual material; and scrapbooks.
85892
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Mr. Cappaert (Donor No. 3192 ) donated his papers to the library in multiple accessions beginning in 1980. Lael Cappaert has added to the collection since then, mainly in 2010.
The collection is open for research.
LeRoy Cappaert was born in 1923 in Silvis, Illinois. His family was the only white family in the neighborhood which primarily consisted of Mexican-American families. The experience had a profound impact on his life. As an adult, he became a vocal supporter of civil rights.
In 1949 he received his AB degree from Augustana College, Rock Island, Illinois. He received his MA in American history from the University of Wisconsin in 1950. In 1953, he began teaching at Tappan Junior High School in Ann Arbor, and in 1959 he became the principal of Pattengill Elementary School. He remained there until 1968, when he became principal of Mack Elementary School.
He served on the Ann Arbor City Council for six years, 1964-1970, and as Mayor Pro-tem in 1969. He was elected as a delegate from Washtenaw County to the Democratic National Convention in Chicago in 1968.
After retiring, he became actively involved with the Coalition for Peace in Central America. The activities of this group focus on aiding Ann Arbor's sister city, Juigalpa, Nicaragua.
Lael Cappaert was a public librarian in Ann Arbor. She was active as well in various political and community organizations.
LeRoy and Lael Cappaert's papers are divided into the following series: Democratic Party politics; Ann Arbor City Council; Personal/Biographical; Family; Coalition for Peace in Central America; Visual Materials; Sound Recordings; and Scrapbooks. Most of the files relate to LeRoy Cappaert's career.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.). Common Council.; Cappaert, Andrea Lael, 1952-1980.; Cappaert, LeRoy.; Coalition for Peace in Central America.; Democratic National Convention (1964: Atlantic City, N.J.); Democratic National Convention (1968: Chicago, Ill.); Democratic Party (Mich.); Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; McCarthy, Eugene J., 1916-2005.; McGovern, George S. (George Stanley), 1922-2012; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party.; Nicaragua.; Presidents--United States--Election--1964.; Presidents--United States--Election--1968.; United States--Politics and government--1963-1969.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Cappaert, Andrea Lael, 1952-1980.; Cappaert, Lael.; Cappaert, LeRoy.; Coalition for Peace in Central America.; Nicaragua.
Contributors:
Cappaert, Lael.
Genre/Form:
Aerial photographs.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Democratic Party Politics 1960-1988
  The Democratic Party Politics series provides information about his campaigns for city council, his activities as a member of the Democratic Party, and his trips to the 1964 and 1968 Democratic National Conventions as a delegate.
  - City Council Campaigns
    - 1963 (Box 1)
    - 1964 (Box 1)
    - 1966
      - Cappaert Campaign (Box 1)
      - Dale Boyd (opponent) (Box 1)
      - Larry McDonald (opponent) (Box 1)
    - 1968 (Box 1)
    - 1970 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1962-1970, undated, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Democratic National Convention
    - Delegate materials 1964, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Delegate materials 1968
      - General and Michigan delegation information, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Clippings (Box 1)
      - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Humphrey, Hubert (Box 1)
      - McCarthy, Eugene (Box 1)
      - McGovern, George (Box 1)
  - Clippings
    - 1960-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1968-1970 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1988 (Box 1)
- Ann Arbor City Council 1962-1970
  The Ann Arbor City Council series includes his correspondence and activities as a council member in Ann Arbor. There are also topical files with information about council issues in which he took an interest.
  - Correspondence
    - 1962-1970 undated, 12 folders (Box 2)
  - Topical files
    - Election reforms 1966-1968 (Box 2)
    - Fair housing and civil rights (Box 2)
    - Police review 1965-1967 (Box 2)
    - Public housing 1960s (Box 2)
    - Race Relations (Pattengill School) (Box 2)
    - Taxicab board (Box 2)
    - Zoning board of appeals (Box 2)
    - Zoning petition (Isberg-Courtelis-Abbott corner) (Box 2)
- Personal/biographical
  The Personal/Biographical series provides information about his personal life and his activities as an educator in the Ann Arbor Public Schools. There is considerable personal information about LeRoy and Lael in the Scrapbook series.
  - Biographical materials (Box 3)
  - Correspondence and related
    - 1949-1959 (Box 3)
    - 1960s-2000, 8 folders (Box 3)
  - Educational career (correspondence) 1960-1988 (Box 3)
  - Hometown (Hero St., Silvis, IL.) (Box 3)
  - Tribute and spoof 1988 (Box 3)
- Family
  The Family series includes memoirs of his Lael Cappaert and a pictorial history of their daughter Andrea Cappaert, a polio survivor.
  - Lael Cappaert
    - Frozen tears (her memoirs), 1999, 2 copies (Box 3)
  - Andrea Lael Cappaert
    - Pictorial history of Andrea Lael Cappaert (originals and copies) (Box 3)
      (The library also has a separately cataloged Andrea Lael Cappaert collection)
- Coalition for Peace in Central America
  The Coalition for Peace in Central America series includes LeRoy Cappaert's notebooks on the organization's activities. The organization's main focus was to provide assistance to Ann Arbor's sister city, Juigalpa, Nicaragua, and to heighten public awareness about the problems in Central America.
  - Notebooks
    - 1985-1986, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1988 (Box 3)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 3)
    - February 25, 1990 (Observation of Nicaraguan elections), 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1990 (Box 4)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 4)
- Visual
  The Visual series includes photographs and videocassettes concerning in part trips to Nicaragua. There are also personal videotapes of programs at which Cappaert was honored.
  - Coalition for Peace in Central America
    - Photographs from trips to Nicaragua (Juigalpa, Ann Arbor's sister city), 1986, 1988, 2 envelopes (Box 4)
    - Slides from Nicaragua trips (Box 4)
    - Videotapes, VHS
      - Booked for Lunch program at Ann Arbor District Library: "Nicaragua Now" December 9, 1986 (Box 4)
      - "Nicaragua Now" November 1986 staff development session, February 2, 1987 (Box 4)
      - Education delegation to Nicaragua November 1988 (Box 4)
      - Proposal A interviews (Channel 7) (Box 4)
      - Reception and editorial November 1988 (Box 4)
      - Ann Arbor Sister City Task Force: Our Sister Juigalpa December 1996 (Box 4)
  - Other activities
    - Miscellaneous photographs (Box 4)
      (include portrait; aerial view of Ann Arbor, 1968 and group portrait that includes LC and Perry Bullard, Ed Pierce, and Greg Ford)
    - Videotapes, VHS
      - Board of Education recognition of LeRoy Cappaert December 9, 1987 (Box 4)
      - Cappaert's last Board of Education meeting June 22, 1988 (Box 4)
        (contains remarks about Cappaert)
      - Packard Community Clinic dedication October 29, 1995 (Box 4)
      - Talk by Deborah Meier: "A vision for our children: transforming public education for a democratic society December 9, 1995 (Box 4)
      - "Thirty years with the Cappaerts 1949-1979" (Box 4)
      - Interview conducted by Hazen Schumacher entitled "Remembering the best LeRoy Cappaert" March 1989 (Box 4)
- Sound Recordings
  The Sound Recordings series consists of reel-to-reel tapes from different periods in Cappaert's life and include interviews with him.
  - Interview by Cappaert with Dr. Butler 1973, audio-cassette (Box 4)
  - City council June 21, 1965, 5 inch; 7.5 ips (Box 4)
  - Interview with State Senator Sander Levin 1967, 2 reels; 5 inch; 7.5 ips (Box 4)
  - Hero St., Silvis, IL., 1 record disk; 45 rpm (Box 4)
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbooks series, covering the period of 1947 to 1980, documents the life and activities of both LeRoy and Lael Cappaert. Included are personal photographs, programs, clippings, letters, and other memorabilia. Personal and explanatory notes are scattered throughout the scrapbooks.
  - 1947-1972, 9 volumes (Box 5)
  - 1973-1980, 8 volumes (Box 6)